Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 8 -- Letters to Franklin 1783 December-1786 Mss.B.F85inventory08
American Philosophical Society
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 August 9; A.L. 1p.; Brillon, Mme
    Cherishes all his letters; he is her Saint whose relies must be sacredly preserved; their undying memory of him and affection for him.
    Printed in Putnam's Monthly, Jan., 1907, 431.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 August 10; A.L.S. 3p.; Chaumont, Jacques-Donatien Le Ray de
    Awaits impatiently the news of Franklin's safe arrival. Disposition made of certain of Franklin's effects. The character of his house entirely changed; nothing but princes and princesses, duchesses and marquises. Makes a suggestion to have large ships so constructed in America that they could come right up the Seine to Paris, laden with timber; thinks there would be profit in such an enterpirse.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 August 10; A.L. 2p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    Description of his return journey after taking leave of Franklin; met by innumerable inquiries from all of Franklin's friends. Condition of the Chateau de la Muette; question of selling the piano-forte. His appreciation of the privilege of having lived with Franklin; his sorrow at losing him and his hope of seeing him return.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 August 10 ?; A.L. 2p.; Le Veillard, Mme. Passy
    Did not follow Franklin's advice to find a consoler; too much grieved by his departure; her children share her sorrow; pleasure she has in possessing his table.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 August 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Whitefoord, Caleb. London
    Acknowledging Franklin's kind letter from Southampton. Envies Mrs. [Mary] Hewson the agreeable society awaiting her in Philadelphia; wishes he were going too; his ungrateful country has done nothing for him. Surprised to hear that the gay Monsieur [William] Temple [Franklin] has retired to the plough.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 August 20; A.L.S. 3p.; Martin, C Barthélemy, fils aîné
    Concerning a bill for £4,500, which he finds it impossible to negotiate in Paris; begs Franklin to cash it for him; promises to repay the money fifteen days or a month before the note's maturity.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 August 20; A.L.S. 4p.; Hare, Georgiana Shipley. Vicenza
    Informed of Franklin's flying visit by her family; could not have borne to see him embark for America, unless she had hopes of going there soon herself; if Franklin gives them the least encouragement, she and her husband will sail for America in the spring; describes her plan of renting a farm near Philadelphia; weary of their present vagabond life; begs for information as to rent, the price of provisions, etc.; asks his advice on many points.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 August 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Hartley, David. London
    Prevented, by absence, from hearing of Franklin's short stay at Southampton. Question of promoting good will and a good understanding between their two countries. Messages from his family.
    Printed in works (Sparks, X, 221; Bigelow, IX, 204).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 September 3; L.S. 3p.; Büyck, Mrs. Pierre. Gand
    Concerning a debt due her and her husband by the State of South Carolina; recounts the particulars and begs Franklin's influence on their behalf.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 September 10; L.S. 3p.; Pierres, Philippe Denis
    Prevented by illness from taking leave of Franklin; his grief at losing him; begs for his continued friendship and for information of any new processes discovered in printing, or new books on the subject; acknowledging the book sent him by Franklin's son.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 September 12; D.S. 3p.; The Masonic Lodge of Carcassonne
    Sending Franklin a copy of their proceedings during the current year. Requests him to recommend L. Carles, one of their members who had gone to America and was then at Mole St. Nicolas, to Chevalier de la Luzerne, Governor of that colony.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 September 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Barbé de Marbois, François
    Congratulating him upon his return to America.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 225; Bigelow, IX, 262).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 September 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Cambray, Col
    Concerning arrears of pay due him for his services in America; wishes to send his certificates to Philadelphia and receive in return the new certificates on which interest is paid annually by M. [Ferdinand] Grand.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 September 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Thomson, Charles. New York
    Congratulating him on his safe arrival and welcoming him to his native country.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 September 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Okely, J. Bethlehem
    Congratulating him on his safe arrival; hopes shortly to do this in person.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 September 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Paine, Thomas. New York
    Congratulating him on his return home. Hopes the evening of his life will resemble Franklin's; feels sure he has never given Franklin reason to regret having been his patron and introducer into America. Prevented from coming to Philadelphia by an interesting affair with Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 September 24; A.L.S. 4p.; Chaumont, Jacques-Donatien Le Ray de
    No news yet of him. Marriage of Mlle. Brillon. Experiments with green wax; desires his son to send him a tun of this wax. Peace between Holland and Germany. Wishes he might live to see the future of America; reflections on that country. Affectionate messages from his family.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 September 24; A.L.S. 1p.; Ogden, Rev'd Uzal. Newark, N. J
    Congratulating him on his safe arrival; feels that he is voicing the desire of the whole State in expressing gratitude for Franklin's eminent services in the cause of freedom; begs his acceptance of two pamphlets just published.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 September 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Edmonds, William. Nazareth, Pa
    Congratulating him on his safe return; hopes he places in Frankin; good wishes for his future welfare.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 September 26; L.S. 3p.; Herbergs, John. Philadelphia
    Petition, as agent, for the heirs and representatives of John Striepers, relative to his claims to land in Pennsylvania and certain lots in the above city originally purchased by John Striepers.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 September 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Childs, Francis
    Welcoming him home; acknowledging his favors of February 8th and April 3d from Paris; would gladly embrace any opportunity of bettering himself under his patronage; desires to know under whtat conditions he aided Mr. [James] Parker; hopes to wait upon him in person.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 September 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Fitch, John
    Informed that the [American] Philosophical Society meets that evening; desires to lay his papers before them; begs leave to postpone sending them to Franklin until the following morning.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 September 28; A.L.S. 3p.; Otto, -------. New York
    Congratulating him upon his safe arrival; France and America equally in his debt for the friendship formed between those two countries; the value of his counsels and experience. Hopes soon to pay his respects to him at Philadelphia and renew his acquaintance with Mr. and Mrs. [Richard] Bache.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 September 30; A.L.S. 4p.; Shipley, Catherine Louisa. Chilbolton
    Sending Georgiana [Shipley Hare]'s verses [4p.]; Georgiana's marriage and the unfortunate circumstances connected with it. News of Sir William Jones. The Slopers at present visiting them. Prefers America to Ireland, there being no Dr. Franklin in the latter country. Sends him a purse with a design of stars and stripes. Report of Franklin's being sent a prisoner to Algiers.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Vernon, William. Newport, R.I
    Congratulates him on his return to America. Asks him to send him an account of his son's conduct in Paris, and the cause of his tarrying there. Also wants his opinion of his son's character. Received no letter from him for four years.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 4; A.L.S. Tho[ma]s Lyttleton, Sec[retar]y. 2p.; The Associates of Dr. Bray
    Purchase, by Dr. Franklin's advice, of a piece of land on Market St. [Philadelphia], by the Associates of Dr. Bray; their present wish to sell part of it; informed by Mr. [Francis] Hopkinson that a new street is to be made near their lot; desires his good offices in this affair on their behalf. Plan for establishing a school for negroes in Philadelphia. Encloses abstracts for their proceedings for the last year, and a book prepared for distribution among the blacks.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 4; A.L.S. 2p.; Jay, John
    Looks to him for the reestablishment of union and harmony in Pennsylvania. Cannot explain why Franklin's letters respecting his grandson [William Temple Franklin] have not been more efficacious. He and Mrs. Jay delighted at the prospect of seeing Dr. Franklin in New York.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 228; Bigelow, IX, 268).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 4; A.L.S. 1p.; Bridgen, Edward
    Just returned from his long tour in the North; greatly improved in health and spirits. Sends the enclosed from the worthy Bishop [of St. Asaph].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Read, John K. Fredericksburgh
    Proposes visiting Philadelphia that winter; looks forward to seeing Franklin. Introducing Mr. Huxham a merchant of fortune and eminence from Charleston; he is accompanied by Mr. Armstrong.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Courtauld, George. Philadelphia
    Brought from England five hundred pounds sterling, also letters of recommendation, from Dr. [Richard] Price; desires to take up farming; asks permission to wait upon him and receive his advice.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Peters, Richard. Belmont, near Philadelphia
    Desires to pay up any deficiency on Franklin's kind advances to his father.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Greene, Caty. Westerly [R. I.]
    Delighted at Franklin's return to America. All her children at home except Ray who is studying law. Greatly honored by Franklin's letter; begs for one of his pictures; the one he sent met with a misfortune; will go and congratulate Sister Mecom on the good news.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, [1785.] October 9; A.L.S. 4p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Acknowledging letters to his brother [Julien David Le Roy] on marine affairs, and to M. Ingen Housz on a new stove for consuming the smoke. Visit paid to M. de Malesherbes in the country; translated Franklin's paper on "Stoves" for publication; curious result of lightning striking M. [Chrétien Guillaume de Lamirgnon de] Malesherbes's dove-cot. Experiments with balloons. Chemists interested in the decomposition of water.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Levers, Robert. Easton, Pennsylvania
    Reviews Franklin's labors for the interest and happiness of America, from the year 1754. Good wishes for his future welfare.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 9; A.L. 2p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    Report of Franklin's capture by the Algerines. Incident of Cardinal de Rohan and the Queen's diamond necklace. Marriages of Mlle. Brillon. Numerous inquiries after Franklin from all his friends. Question of Franklin's memoirs.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 230; Bigelow, IX, 270).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Ellery, William. New York
    At the request of William Vernon, Esq., late of the Navy Board of the United States, sends his letters.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Paca, William. Annapolis
    Congratulating him on his safe return. Enclosing a letter from Dr. [John] Shuttleworth who has lost considerable property through the confiscation laws; his intention of bringing the matter before the Assembly; thinks the Doctor's interview with Franklin at Passy will carry great weight if endorsed by a line from Franklin; begs this favor for his friend.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 10; A.L.S. 1p.; Bush, David. Wilmington, Delaware
    Delighted at the reception accorded Franklin; congratulates him on all that he has done for America; recalls the old days when their small Club used to meet; all gone now except Franklin and himself. News of his family.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 12; A.L.S. 1p.; Fitch, John. Bucks County Pennsylvania
    The great advantages of his steamboat; desires Franklin's assistance in introducing another useful art into the world.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 232).
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 13; A.L.S. 4p.; Sears and Smith. New York
    Concerning the retention, by Revenue Officers at Martinique, of a cargo of negroes landed there by their ship "Fire-brand"; these slaves will be sold unless a heavy duty is paid on every one; protest against such treatment and beg Franklin's good offices with the French Government; aware this is an unfavorable subject with which to trouble him; can only assure him that this trade in negroes was purely accidental.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Milligan, James
    Concerning the arrears of pay due Col. Cambray; will obtain a certificate for the full amount including interest and transmit it to Col. Cambray by whatever channel Franklin advises.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Geiger, Henry. Heidelberg Township Penna
    Congratulating Franklin upon his safe arrival and on his election as President of the Commonwealth of Pennsylvania; good wishes for his future welfare.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Gates, Horatio. Berkeley Co., Virginia
    Congratulating him on his auspicious return to the Nation whose independence he has principally contributed to establish. Has not received one farthing of the principal or interest of the thousands owing him by the united States; his estate almost ruined; can't afford to leave it to pay his respects to Franklin. Great hopes from Franklin's election as head of Pennsylvania; thinks he alone can reconcile parties and bring peace to that divided land.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 14; A.L.S. Nath[anie]l Falconer, John M'Culloh, Sam[ue]l Miles, Judges of the past election. 1p.; The Judges of Election. Philadelphia
    As Judges of the past election they acquaint him that he is elected Counsellor for the City of Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 13; A.L.S. 3p.; Shuttleworth, John. Annapolis, Md
    Begs him to certify to Governor Paca certain details of their conversation at Passy; value of such testimony in enabling him to recover a part of his confiscated estate.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 17; A.L.S. 1p.; Biddle, John. Philadelphia
    Has petitioned the Supreme Executive Council [of Pennsylvania] to appoint him head measurer of salt and grain; hopes he may meet with Franklin's approbation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 17; A.L.S. 2p.; Menou, Comtesse de
    Begging for news of Franklin; all kinds of rumors flying about Paris. Recommending a young man of good family, and some talent, but no fortune.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Bard, John and Susanna
    Congratulating him on his return to his native land; sorry he cannot enjoy the repose he had so amply earned. Their removal from the country to New York; news of his family; deaths and marriages. Praise for young Mr. [William Temple] Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 22; A.L.S. 1p.; Wharton, Samuel. Southwark
    Has been ill but hopes to wait upon Franklin in a day or two relative to Dr. Ingen Housz's business.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 24; A.L.S. 2p.; Reynolds, Thomas. Philadelphia Gaol
    Confined for seven months past without trial, on suspicion of a trifling offense; his services in the American navy; has applied to the Navy Office for the prize-money due him; informed that they could not settle his claims until they received the returns from Franklin; begs his assistance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Tackett, Nathanie. Philadelphia
    Sending Franklin a copy of a memorial now before Congress, concerning a plan for the settlement of a new state.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 25; A.L.S. 3p.; Bays, ----- de. Nuits
    Offering him wines of the first quality.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 25; A.L.S. 1p.; Robinson, Rachal. Philadelphia
    Widow of James Robinson, who commanded the ship which carried Franklin to England. During his Continental service, her husband captured a schooner bound from Providence to New York, which was taken from him by the French fleet; this action approved of by Mr. Livingston and later by Congress; desires to wait on Franklin in reference to this affair.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Croker (now Mead), Catherine
    Pleasure with which she heard of his arrival; all her father's relatives dead but Dr. Franklin; begs him to write to her.
    1 [Niece of Benjamin Franklin.]
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 28; A.L.S. 3p.; Le Roy, Jean Baptiste
    Informed of Franklin's arrival in America; his enthusiastic reception and his improved state of health; all Paris rejoiced at the news. Prophesies that his presence will infuse new life into the [American] Philosophical Society of Philadelphia. Death of his eldest brother. Experiments with balloons.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 29; A.L.S. 4p.; Sharp, Granville. Old Jewry, London
    His views concerning the election of bishops; his objections to the non-giving bishops of Scotland; his reasons for wishing that the first American bishops should receive their consecration from English bishops. Acknowledging the information concerning the abbreviated liturgy; reasons why the Psalms cannot be curtailed.
    Printed, for the most part, in Mass. Hist. Soc. Collections, III, 162.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 30; A.L.S. 1p.; Longchamps, ------. Prison of Philadelphia
    Congratulations on his election [as President of the Supreme Executive Council of Pennsylvania].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 30; A.L.S. 3p.; Le Veillard, Louis Guillaume
    Keen pleasure felt by Franklin's friends at the reception accorded him in Philadelphia; compares his entry to the ancient triumphs at Rome, to the latter's disadvantage. Reminds him of his promise to write the memoirs of his life; insists on the importance of such a work. Tremendous jealousy and dissension caused by Franklin's writing to one fair friend and ignoring the other; humorous account of the affair. Occupations of the Court at Fontaincbleau. Postponement of the Cardinal de Rohan's trial.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 31; A.L.S. 1p.; Vanderen, John Jr. Philadelphia
    Hopes his petition to the Supreme Executive Council, asking to be appointed Notary Public, will meet with Franklin's approbation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October 31; A.L.S. 1p.; Childs, Francis
    Congratulations on his late appointment [as President of Pennsylvania]; fears the burden of such an office will be too great a tax on his health. Question concerning type.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 October; A.L.S. 1p.; Sargent, Rosamond. London
    Has been so ill that she doubted ever being able again to express her regard for Franklin; congratulates him on his return to America; hopes the new country will make a proper use of her independence. Introducing a relative of hers to Franklin's good offices; her husband has written also.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 November 1; A.L. 1p.; S-----, M-----. Chestnut Hill
    Submits his jeu d'esprit to his superior judgment, and he hopes it will be suppressed if not approved.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 November 5; A.L. 2p.; Brillon, Mme
    Informed of his arrival in his own country and the honors he has received. Her grief over their separation ineffaceable. News of her family. Praise of Franklin's character.
    Printed in Putnam's Monthly, Jan., 1907, 434.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 November 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Timothy, Ann. Charleston
    Congratulations on his safe return and on his devoted services to his country. His friendship for her late husband [Peter Timothy]; has brought up her son to be worthy of the illustrious name he bears; would have sent him to see Franklin had the season not been so far advanced.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 November 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Thomson, Charles. New York
    Congratulating him on his present promotion; hopes his prudence will allay the heats and temper the ferments of parties. Concerning the wish of Franklin's grandson [William Temple Franklin] to be employed in some public office abroad; thinks he has a well-grounded claim to it; advises a seat in the National Council for a year or two as a good preparation.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 November 5; A.L.S. 2p.; Price, Richard. Newington Green
    Account of a remedy for the stone. Delighted to hear of his safe arrival and flattering reception. Regrets not having been with him at Southampton. Acknowledging his election as member of the [American] Philosophical Society; desires Franklin to convey his thanks to the President and other members. Hostile aspect of affairs between England and America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 November 6; A.L.S. 3p.; Lopes, Toussaint. New York
    Petition for arrears of pay due him for his services in the American army; his pleas to Congress have elicited no reply; begs Franklin to assist him; the money will pay his debts and enable him to return to France.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 November 7; A.L.S. 2p.; Bridgen, Edward
    Dr. [Richard] Price has entrusted to his care the accompanying book by the late Dr. Dobson. Inquires if he shall continue to pay Franklin's annual dues at the Society of Antiquaries [of London].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 November 9; A.L.S. 4p.; 2p.; Limozin, Andrew. London
    Discharged Franklin's servant, Charles Hicks; his obvious disappointment and dissatisfaction; his loss of the Angora cat; believes he sold it. Enclosing bills of lading for various articles shipped; as to his own commission, begs Franklin to accept it.
    Statement of freight, etc., on personal effects of Benjamin Franklin shipped to Philadelphia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 November 12; A.L.S. 2p.; Armbruster, Anthony. Germantown
    Congratulations on his election as President of Pennsylvania. Account of his unfortunate treatment during Franklin's absence abroad; sued for a debt of seventeen pounds; put in gaol and all the stock of his printing-office sold; his long struggle against poverty; his present work in a printing office in Germantown; desires a candid consideration of his case.
  - to W.T. Franklin, 1785 November 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Lawrence, Jno
    Sends the enclosed letter from Col. Shre(e)ve, concerning the necessary repairs on the river bank; has Franklin's deed for the park, etc.; will leave it with his son, during his absence from town.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 November 16; A.L.S. 3p.; Chaumont, Jacques-Donatien Le Ray de
    Mme. de Chaumont occupies Franklin's old rooms; their constant talk of him; hopes to pay him a visit. Treaty between Holland and the [Holy Roman] Emperor, [Joseph II]; signed under the guarantee of the King of France; M. de Vergennes a great peace-maker. Disadvantages to America of a too rapid emigration. M. de la Motte occupied with medicine.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 November 16; L. 1p.; -------, -------
    Requests him to obtain a piece of land near Pennsbury for Mrs. [Patience] Wright, to be used as a burial ground.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1785 November 20; A.L.S. 1p.; Oswald, Elizabeth